the following is a production of Frankie
Freitas and the internet review of
holography
ladies and gentlemen at this stage we
introduce the subject himself here that
you will perceive fits and well
nourished he come straight from the
night pink and the good breakfast and
hypnotized tomorrow we send him out with
confidence into the world again
hello this is Franklin and welcome to
holotalk the internet laser and
holography talk show our toll-free
number is
[Music]
1-800-458-3525 or you can send an email
to holotalk
poloworld.com we've got telephone calls
we've got emails we've got special
guests coming up so thank you for tuning
in and let's get this week's show on the
road
hello folks and welcome to another week
of holotalk this is Frankie Freitas I
want to wish you a happy New Year
our guest tonight is Alex shimetz from a
company called three deep company and
Alex is a importer of the new Russian
emotions who are going to be speaking
with him about that a little bit later
on I'm also going to be going over some
of the technical information about these
emulsions after we do that interview our
musical guest this week is a band called
Cigar and they're out of Eugene Oregon
so we'll be hearing from cigar a little
bit later on as well
we got a few email questions this week
let's go to our first one this is from
Allison and Allison writes the whole
talk she says I'd love to start doing
Holograms but I live in a small
apartment could you tell me how much
space I would need and do I need a dark
room okay Allison
um space is not too much of a problem
with holography I remember doing
Holograms in very small setups and
actually if you're going to start out
doing very simple Holograms you don't
need one of the big isolation tables
that you see in the labs across the
country
remember when you're doing a single beam
reflection hologram and that's what most
holographers do when they start out
doing holography or just single beam
Holograms and I don't think a lot of
people are aware of this but you do not
need to have the laser isolated the
laser can be sitting on any tabletop or
anything that you want to sit it on just
as is what you need to have isolated
first single beam reflection hologram is
the plate holder and the object being
recorded
so considering the fact if you've got a
5 or 10 milliwatt laser to start out
you're probably going to be working with
plate sizes that are about two and a
half by two and a half inches or four by
five inches
the only space requirements you would
need to do that hologram would be enough
space to have that plate holder however
you want to set that up and the object
isolated now there's a few different
ways that you can do this you can get a
very small inner tube not the type of
inner tubes from a car but the type of
inner tube that comes from a forklift
truck and you can find them at any
industrial supplier and they're tiny
little tires or maybe about a foot or 18
inches
in diameter
and on top of that little tire you can
place a heavy object now there's a
couple different ways you can approach
this you can get a piece of metal
a metal surface that you can sit down on
that that actually has a lot of weight
itself or you can choose something like
a large patio block I think there's 24
by 24 inch patio blocks that you could
sit down on top of that tire table this
is going to give you your vibration
isolation that you're going to need just
for the plate holder and the object
itself on top of that surface you need
to place whatever plate holder you've
managed to make for yourself and the
object itself make sure that both of
these things are stable that is you need
a nice stable object you can't pick
something flimsy because even with the
best holographic setup if you've got a
flimsy object you're going to get poor
results in the final hologram make sure
your object is very stable and just go
ahead and do your exposure your laser
and your beam expanding lens itself does
not have to be on that Isolation part of
the setup it can be sitting anywhere
that you want it to sit in fact if you
want to just do it right down on the
floor
now as far as a dark room
I know a lot of people
that use their bathrooms for dark rooms
this has good and bad things to go along
with it the good thing is
it's right there it's handy now you
don't have to go up or down a flight of
steps from say for instance you're going
to do your development down in the
basement of the apartment building or
something like that you don't have to do
that because you have your bathroom
right there
the only thing I get concerned about
sometimes is actually ventilation
now keep in mind this is not photography
this is holography you're not going to
be going into a dark room and making 36
or 72 prints you're just not going to do
that with Holograms usually you'll set
up and do one two maybe three Holograms
a night and you've got time in between
those two because you have to go back
out of the dark room again to do the
next setup now I would suggest that if
you have a small window get a window fan
and the way that you're going to get
around having light come in is I want
you to make a hood to go over the
outside of that small window fan now we
don't need a big window fan we just need
a small one and
make a hood so that it sort of caps that
fan and the only way that the air can
get out from the fan as an exhaust is
through the bottom of that hood
now if you have screens I would suggest
that you double up on the screens take
your screens which are normally a
silverish material and spray paint them
a flat black and you're going to spray
paint two screens
put one of the screens in the window and
then put the other screen in the window
and if they're slightly offset you're
not going to see any light coming
through because of the obvious small
openings in the screen to begin with
along with the black paint and the hood
you have on your fan
so this will give you a little bit of
ventilation but I don't think you have
too much of a problem just being in
there to develop a hologram especially
if you're using your traditional type of
development chemicals like your d19s and
things of that nature so yes you can do
Holograms in an apartment very easily
and if you find that you want to make
Holograms that are a little bit more
complex than your single beam Holograms
you can move up to a few of the uh
systems that you can buy that sit on the
neoprene isolation balls that you can
buy so there's all kinds of ways of
doing it you don't have to not do
holography just because you live in an
apartment
our second email question comes from
Chris and Chris writes in this is a very
interesting question I wonder how many
holotalk listeners could answer this
question what was the first hologram
made of
and I'm assuming Chris you mean made of
as far as an image the content of the
Hologram rather than the materials that
the Hologram was shot on
the early Holograms even the first
hologram was made without using a laser
sodium vapalamp was used to make the
first hologram sodium vapor lamps are
just like those lamps when you're
driving down the street at night they
illuminate the street
and these lights
do not contain the entire range of the
visible spectrum as far as wavelengths
are concerned and they can be through
careful filtering filtered down to be a
monochromatic light source however the
problem with using something like that
for a hologram is there is another
property that's needed to make a
hologram and that is called coherence
length and it is the coherence length
this property that allows us to record
the depth of a hologram
now the coherence length of a sodium
vapor lamp is very short
extremely short in fact the first
hologram could only record the depth of
a postage stamp
and that first hologram was actually
something about the size of a postage
stamp and it had the names of several
physicists on it so it wasn't actually a
true
three-dimensional image although it
contained the third dimension enough to
show the depth of that piece of paper or
postage stamp size material but it
wasn't anything that you would walk into
a museum and say wow this is really
something so that's what the first
hologram was it was made with the sodium
vapor lamp and it was a postage size
stamp which contained the names
of very famous physicists
just as a reminder you can send in your
questions to holotalk two ways
the first way is to send it in by
telephone you can call a toll-free
number and that number is
1-800-458-3525 and we'll put your
question on the air or you can send an
email to holotalk at holoworld.com I'll
read your question and answer it on the
air so if you have any questions about
lasers and Holograms send them through
we'll get them on the air and I'm sure
other people that are listening have the
same questions so to appreciate hearing
them
our third email question actually can be
tied into the interview that's coming up
with Alex shimetz and this was sent in
by Scott and Scott wrote I know that
agrofilms and plates will not be
available much longer and I know that
other companies are trying to pick up a
slack but what's really bothering me is
the exposure time involved with this new
film I was looking at buying a five
milliwatt laser to get me started with
holography but it seems now that this
may not be a suitable laser for this new
film
so my question is what kind of laser
would be best for the new film
well Scott we're going to go over this
now with Alex we just finished the
interview actually it's 11 30 on
Saturday night the show goes up at 12 30
and I just finished talking with Alex at
10 30 so
we just got this in right under the gun
both of our schedules this week were
nearly impossible with the New Year's
Day holiday and everything tied in this
week but we still managed to pull it
through for everybody and this is an
important issue because as everyone is
probably aware of on Earth that's
involved with holography
agfa has discontinued making their
materials their Holo test materials that
we were so used to working with in our
professional labs and in our amateur and
hobbyist lab as well
so we're looking for something to take
the place of AG film
and we have some materials here that
Alex is going to tell us about it's made
at a plant and slavage and
they're looking very promising so we'll
let Alex tell us a little bit about
these materials Alex is a person who
Imports the materials
I have some technical information after
the interview is over I'd like to go
over some of the technical
specifications of these emulsions with
you just so that you know how these
emotions compared with Agatha I went
through some of my materials here at the
studio and found some of access
specification sheets as well so I'll
compare it to a one-to-one comparison
from what I have on agfa compared to the
new Russian emulsions so let's move on
to our interview with Alex at 3deep
company is the name of the company
that's importing these emulsions they
have a website it's
www.3deep pump three deep coat excuse me
uh three d e e p c o.com that's
www.3dco.com there's also a link on the
main hall talk page where you can go
over and take a look at this uh website
I was over on a website and I have to
tell you it's a wealth of information on
the materials
if you're confused about this as many
people are including myself
um there's a forum
that you can see where all the all the
people have sent in their questions
about these materials as far as getting
better results how to make really nice
Holograms with them
and other holographers who have been
working with these materials for a while
log on and they answer some of the
questions it's a very nice feature so if
you want to head over there you can
actually cruise that website while
you're listening to the whole talk show
itself
so let's go over in that
talk with Alex I'm sending this through
to you unedited and uncut because there
is not enough time to work with it
tonight being that it's 11 30 already
and I really like to keep on schedule
and have this up at midnight so um let's
go talk to Alex
okay we're ready to go
okay we're talking to Alex shimet who is
with three deep company that's correct
isn't it that's right 3D company and
you're involved with basically bringing
these emotions into the United States
now is that correct that's true we've
been working uh together with uh slavich
for about four years a little bit over
four years I remember a few years ago
getting it was either something in the
mail or even a phone call from you
saying that you were working with these
emotions and we were all aware of the
high quality emotions that were being
produced in Russia but of course nobody
really paid any attention to it because
you could just get a box of eggs and go
your Merry way now that's no longer the
case and I imagine you have quite a bit
of interest in these emulsions right now
that's right uh we um when I first
started it was uh you know smuggling
plates out of the country from a trip
and uh talking calling some people such
as yourself to get them tested but it
was uh it was really a hurry up and wait
kind of a procedure because um
there's a lot of problems with changing
from one Emulsion to another and I know
that holographers don't want to do it if
they don't have to and as of February
they have to yeah there's not much of a
choice now
I imagine anyone who's involved with
mass production of plates and film
already pretty much have an idea what's
going on with these emulsions but the
big question lies with the school groups
the amateurs that are out there doing
holography as a hobby now even though
this is just people these are just
people who are just going to call up and
order a box of plates maybe every month
or every two months or something like
that
where are we with these people if
they're in a school or they're in their
basement doing Holograms with maybe a
five or a 10 milliwatt laser will they
be able to make some sort of holographic
images with this with this Emulsion well
there's uh there's been some experience
there was a it was a kid out of I think
it was Connecticut who who took some of
our plates and at that time we had very
little experience working with amateurs
he had uh it was for one of his classes
and he bought a couple boxes and he
tried it out using chemicals from the
one of the states like Michigan or
Wisconsin or something like that I think
and he he was able to uh get a number of
images
um it wasn't perfect I mean he was an
amateur and I I'm not a holographer I'm
an importer there was little that I
could offer him
uh it did get me to thinking that uh
when we put together our website
um that we should the people who are
going to know the most about making
Holograms using the slavish plates are
the people who are using them and buying
them from me not necessarily
me or or even or slavich because this is
a new chemical formulation that
everybody's going to be using they're
not necessarily going to use the Russian
chemical formulations so we put together
a discussion forum so that amateurs and
professionals could get out to what's
been working what's not been working and
the experiences of some amateurs are on
the discussion forum so that it has been
working it's not a straight b19
formulation it's been working the best
but the
some adjustments and then they put it on
the site
can you buy pre-packaged chemistry to go
with these plates
yeah we don't Supply chemistry okay is
it available anywhere that you could get
it pre-packaged because every place that
I've seen they give you the actual
formulations for making your developer
and things of that nature but I haven't
seen anything where it just comes maybe
as a powder where you just Add Water
yeah at this moment I'm investigating a
lab out of San Francisco
client there's also a company called
Sigma several other companies as well
Jordan which is a an old agfa
distributor out of Michigan Ann Arbor
Michigan they've had certain chemicals I
don't know that they stock all the
chemicals used for the slavage plates
right now there's different formulations
going around people are using and
testing different formulations I would
say that at this stage today for amateur
holography if someone were to take some
of these plates and amateur and try
something out he would be not
necessarily breaking new ground I mean
there's there's been work done and
there's been things published on the
site and elsewhere but definitely would
be increasing the overall knowledge I
was out on your site and it is a wealth
of information as far as these new
recording materials and I think the
Forum is a very good idea because I
spent quite a bit of time reading the
different questions that were sent in
and then other holographers they'll log
on and do responses to the question
the website address I I know you have
your own domain name now is that correct
that's right the the website address is
uh
www dot
pco.com or basically
www.3deepcode.com okay with the
numerical three the numerical three
we'll we'll also have a link directly to
your site and if you're listening to the
show right now there's no need to just
sit there and stare at the computer
while it talks to you you can go back
into your browser and go right to the
site as you continue to listen to the
show
um for my group of people and I mostly
get amateurs and educational services
and things of that nature at the site
that's the majority of people that come
through the site but I imagine they
would be interested in two types of the
emotions the
pfg-01 and the
pfd-03m that's true that's what I would
guess for the helium neon users yes now
I I received the package from slavish
this week and it does say
pfg-01 is good for laser transmission
and reflection holography is that true
well there's uh this 201 there's a pfg01
which is um As I understood it to be
transmission with pulse laser or helium
neon and then there's an 01m which is a
slight Improvement uh it doesn't have an
anti-hale um halation backing and it's
for transmission and reflection I see
and it has a greater it's actually a
faster Emulsion than the O3 that's right
it is a faster Emulsion okay because
I've got some of ags's older information
here from their eighties
75 HD emotions
and it appears to me that it may be
possible to make reflection Holograms
with this said
Dash zero one Emulsion and is there one
the analog zero one would be the 8075
and the o1m the analog would be an 8 e75
HD uh the oims are not uh that we don't
have them yet they won't arrive until
mid-January
but at the moment we're we're reducing
our buys of the 01 that's straight for
transmission because it looks like the
o1m is really going to support just
about everybody's needs if there's our
if there are special needs requiring the
older the older type Emulsion of course
we'd be happy to pick that up on the
next uh restocking purchase okay and
from what I understand there's no
bleaching involved at all with the O3
emulsions for the reflection Holograms
which I found out very fascinating
uh you're getting into a technical level
okay okay we'll we'll probably cover
this after the interview's over because
I have all the technical information
here maybe we can do a little Tech talk
after uh we say goodbye and I'll I'll go
over all these numbers with everyone
okay but that's what I find absolutely
fascinating because there was a time
where you just could not do a reflection
hologram without having a bleach process
it's just what the emotion itself just
wasn't efficient enough to replay that
image but with these new emulsions
there's no bleaching Step At All uh
anything else you want to let the
listeners know about your services and
how they can contact you and order some
of these I understand you may have a
a little test package that you can send
out to someone if they'd like to order
that is that true well it's actually uh
the all the packaging on this on these
on the slavich plates are are very
amateur friendly they're um they're
small they're small boxes so if we if
there was an interest in two and a half
by two and a half inch plates well
they're packed sticks to a plate and the
four by five plates are packed uh four
to a plate
we have a special going on now for
first-time buyers and uh for the it's
really the specials only for the 4x5
plates but it's quite good for the
pfg03m plates which is for the for the
helium Neon
for the helium neon wheel we offer four
plates for it for U.S orders uh twenty
dollars plus five dollars shipping for
Canadian orders it's uh twenty dollars
plus eight dollars shipping day two and
a half plates are four by five these are
for four by five okay
and it's only uh I mean it's only a
little bit more than the two and a half
by two and a half and that's right where
agfa was right now and that was what we
were trying to do uh right now pricing
is all over the place and and the
Russians are learning their new cost
structure too as as their prices rise
and fall with the their changing economy
so it's been it's been difficult and I
think one of the advantages that it is
for for for a U.S American I guess
International holographers having three
deep around is that we you know we level
we balance out all of the the changing
problems and demands and situation in
Russia by keeping inventory in the
United States and by keeping the prices
steady
can they order chemistry through you I
don't know if you said that or not no at
this stage no no chemistry all right so
we're looking to the chemical supplier
for this also along with you in the show
tonight
uh okay well Alex I know you have to run
you're going out for dinner I hope you
enjoy it and um I'm glad we were able to
get in touch with one another oh yeah I
got the last moment folks it's it's 10
30 on Saturday night the show goes up at
midnight so I don't think we could get
any closer than this
well I mean I just want to say one more
thing I mean this is a whole thing since
February has been very exciting and I
not that I wanted to you know I'm happy
that holographers have the the best
place out there and that they're using
something that's familiar but since agfa
has decided to pull out there has been I
mean for for three deep there's been so
many so many changes uh we put on the
website we took we got credit card
acceptance so we can we can take credit
card orders people from around the world
are looking to try it out so I and
they've been happy I mean we've got
we've gotten uh not just the first order
but we're getting the second order so I
think that the slavage plates are going
to turn out to be
um you know not second ones but I think
opening up a whole new a whole new level
of art a whole new level of resolution
and it's going to change the way
holography works in the future do I want
to wish you a lot of luck thank you very
much Frank thanks for calling and thanks
for being on the show great Alex take
care okay bye-bye
okay we're back in the studio let me
just get situated with all the papers
that I have all over here
and see if we can't go over some of the
technical specifications here
uh what should I read let's see
introduction let's just read a quick
introduction on the company itself the
company
slavich.js company
situated at oh good luck
well they are 130 kilometers from Moscow
let's just put it that way it's
currently a leading manufacturer of
photographic plates for the micro
electronics Industry
conventional photographic papers and of
audio and video tapes in addition to
these products slavich has been
producing for many years high quality
holographic materials
the production of photographic plates
and of the holographic materials is
carried out in facilities located in the
Micron plant a Slavic subsidiary
Enterprise the Micron plant produces
holographic materials on hard glass and
flexible film bases a list and brief
description of these materials are
presented Below in table one okay
so I have some material here which goes
back
to the active materials
let's take a look at how these things
line up with one another now in the
interview
Alex mentioned the
pfg-01 now on my sheet here it says It's
A fine grain red sensitive holographic
plate and film designed for transmission
or reflection hologram recording
average grain size is 40 nanometers
resolving power more than three thousand
lines per millimeter and the spectral
sensitivity range is from 600 to 680
nanometers with the Peaks
at 633 which is our helium neon line and
647.
now let's move down to agfa
and I'm going to look here now at 875 HD
which was the recording material of
choice where reflection holography with
ag from materials
now this is just a a chart so there's no
text with it so grain size 35 nanometers
35 nanometers now the grain size with
the slavage plates
40 nanometers not too much of a
difference there 35 for the agfa 40. for
the slavage
resolving lines per millimeter
five thousand
lines per millimeter for agfa
Slavic revolving excuse me resolving
power more than three thousand lines per
millimeter
now will it be possible to do reflection
Holograms with these plates now Alex had
mentioned a
pfg-01m which is going to be close to
the sensitivity of the ad for materials
let's move on to the
pfg-03m with
ultra fine grain red sensitive plates
and film designed for reflection
hologram recording
average grain size is 8 to 12 nanometers
that's small resolving power more than
five thousand lines per millimeter and
the spectral sensitivity range includes
633 nanometers
647 nanometers as well
now this is where we run into the
sensitive sensitivity issue and that is
that the Emulsion actually has to be
exposed
for quite a bit more time than with the
bag for plates
so there let's go through here and see
what we have here
okay we have the processing the
diffraction efficiency
for the
pfg-03n is greater than 45 percent
that's incredible so if these are done
correctly you could expect to get very
bright Holograms from them
very bright Holograms so that's how they
compare side to side comparison so the
pfg-01 the
the whole the whole graphic materials
that they're saying can be used for both
transmission and reflection hologram
recording seem to be very close to where
the agfa 8e75 HD
that we're all familiar with it's the
pfg-03n Emulsion which is going to need
quite a bit of a hit from the light
source in order to get
uh good results so there we have it
okay so that just about wraps it up for
another show I hope between the show and
if you traveled over to the 3D company
website that you had a few of your
questions answered concerning these new
recording materials that we have to work
with
our entertainment this week for your
listening pleasure is a band called
cigar out of Eugene Oregon and if you go
back to the whole talk page you'll see
the link to listen to them if you choose
to listen to them they do come through
at 28 8 so that's a 28 8 recording in
real audio
5.0 so if you do not have real audio 5.0
this show probably will not work for you
so I want to thank you for tuning in and
I hope you stop back next week
this is Frankie Freitas for holotalk
have a great week and happy New Year